John DeWitt
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
John DeWitt papers
1962-1979
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
DeWitt, John
1.4 linear feet
The scattered papers of federal arts administrator John DeWitt date from 1962-1979, and measure 1.4 linear feet. The collection primarily documents 1970s arts programs sponsored by the U.S. Bureau of Reclamation, an agency of the Department of the Interior. Found within the papers are correspondence concerning the department's art projects and exhibition files for The American Artist and Water Reclamation, 1972, and America 1976.
Provenance
The John DeWitt papers were donated in 1987 by DeWitt's widow, Miriam Hapgood DeWitt.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
John DeWitt was born in 1910 and was a wood sculptor and federal arts administrator in Washingon, D.C.
DeWitt began his career as a professional writer and was a wood sculptor connected with the Veerhoff Gallery in Washington, D.C. His wife, Miriam Hapgood DeWitt, was a painter. In the late 1960s, DeWitt was the Director of Art Programs for the Bureau of Reclamation, an agency of the Department of Interior responsible for water conservation in arid regions of the United States. At this time, the Bureau initiated a program to present its accomplishments to the public through arts commissions and exhibitions. Under the direction of DeWitt and Lloyd Goodrich of the Whitney Museum of American Art, some 40 artists including Ralston Crawford, Peter Hurd, and Norman Rockwell, were invited to depict the scope of reclamation projects in the American West. The artists were given a free hand to depict any scene in any medium as long as the subject matter pertained to the Bureau of Reclamation's program. The resulting artwork was displayed in an exhibition, The American Artist and Water Reclamation, that opened at the National Gallery of Art in April 1972, and then toured the country in a traveling exhibition sponsored by the Smithsonian Institution.
As the Director of the Visual Arts Program for the Department of the Interior, DeWitt celebrated the Bicentennial by organizing the exhibition America 1976, for which he hired over forty realist painters including Vija Celmins, Ralston Crawford, Alex Katz, Philip Pearlstein, and Wayne Thiebaud, to depict a diverse range of Americana. DeWitt was employed by the Department of the Interior until 1977.
John DeWitt died in 1984.
Scope and Content Note
The scattered papers of federal arts administrator John DeWitt date from 1962-1979, and measure 1.4 linear feet. The collection primarily documents 1970s arts programs organized by DeWitt while working for the U.S. Bureau of Reclamation, an agency of the Department of the Interior. Found within the papers are scattered correspondence concerning the department's art projects, including the Preservation of Endangered Species Art Program and activities of the Hereward Lester Cooke Foundation. There are letters from artists Vija Celmins, Lamar Dodd, and Ethel Magafan.
Files for the two exhibitions organized by DeWitt for the U.S. Bureau of Reclamation, The American Artist and Water Reclamation and America 1976, include a wide variety of materials. There are correspondence, lists of artwork, printed materials, a scrapbook, financial materials, audio recordings of interviews with DeWitt, audio recordings of a symposium on America 1976, and numerous photographs of exhibited artwork and participating artists. There are also additional photographs of DeWitt and his colleagues and artists Joseph Raffael and Ann Wyeth McCoy.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 3 series; each series is arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1965-1979 (Box 1; 10 folders)
Series 2: Exhibition Files, 1962-1978 (Box 1, 2; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 3: Photographs, 1970-1974 (Box 2; 1 folder)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
McCoy, Ann Wyeth; Raffael, Joseph, 1933-; Hereward Lester Cooke Foundation; United States. Bureau of Reclamation; America 1976 (1976-1978 -- Washington, D.C.); American artist and water reclamation (1973 -- Washington, D.C.)
Subjects-Topical:
Arts administrators --Washington (D.C.)
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Scrapbooks; Interviews; Sound recordings
Names:
aCelmins, Vija, 1939-; Dodd, Lamar; Magafan, Ethel, 1915 or 6-1993
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Correspondence, 1965-1979, Series 1:; (Box 1; 10 folders)
  General correspondence discusses miscellaneous proposed art projects for the Bureau of Reclamation, most notably the Preservation of Endangered Species Art Program. There are scattered letters from Vija Celmins, Lamar Dodd,and Ethel Magafan, and a photocopy of a letter from Miriam Hapgood DeWitt's father, Hutchins Hapgood to Bernard Berenson, discussing Berenson's books, their friendship and Hapgood's travels on the Amalfi coast of Italy.
  - Correspondence, 1965-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence Concerning the Preservation of Endangered Species Art Program, 1974-1977, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Correspondence Concerning the Hereward Lester Cooke Foundation, 1975-1979, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
- Exhibition Files, 1962-1978, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-2; 1.3 linear feet)
  Exhibition files concern two exhibitions, The American Artist and Water Reclamation in 1972 and America 1976. Files contain a wide variety of materials, such as scattered correspondence, a drawing by William Palmer, scattered financial material, lists of exhibited artwork, miscellaneous notes, a scrapbook, clippings, exhibition catalogs; photographs of scenes of the American West; photographs of participating artists including Vija Celmins, Hereward Lester Cooke, Ralston Crawford, Richard Diebenkorn, Lamar Dodd, Michael Frary, Xavier Gonzalez, Peter Hurd, Billy Morrow Jackson, Mitchell Jamieson, Dong Kingman, Ethel Magafan, Carl Morris, William Palmer, Norman Rockwell, and Fritz Scholder; and phtotographs of their artwork. There is also an album of photographs of the opening of the exhibition The American Artist and Water Reclamation. Audio recordings on cassettes and reel-to-reel tapes contain interviews concerning the exhibition, as well as a tape of a symposium on the exhibition America 1976.
  - The American Artist and Water Reclamation, 1962-1974, undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Drawing by William Palmer, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - List of Artwork, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Scrapbook, 1969-1973, (7 folders) (Box 1, Folder 15-21)
    - Clippings, 1971-1974, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
    - Exhibition Catalog, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Photographs of Glen Canyon, Utah, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Photographs of Miscellaneous Canyons, 1962-1974, (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 26-31)
    - Photographs of Vincent Arcilesi, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Photographs of Elmer Bischoff, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Photographs of Vija Celmins and Hereward Lester Cooke, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Photographs of Ralston Crawford, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Photographs of Horace Day and James Dean, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Photographs of Lamar Dodd, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Photographs of Ethel Edwards and Dean Fausett, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Photographs of Michael Frary, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Photographs of Lloyd Lozes Goff and Xavier Gonzalez, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Photographs of Peter Hurd, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Photographs of Billy Morrow Jackson and Mitchell Jamieson, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Photographs of Dong Kingman, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Photographs of Edward Laning and Ethel Magafan, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Photographs of Herman Maril and Fletcher Martin, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Photographs of Alfred McAdams and Carl Morris, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Photographs of William Palmer, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Photographs of Roland Peterson, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Photographs of Norman Rockwell, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Photographs of Fritz Scholder, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Photographs of Arthur Smith, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Photographs of Unidentified Artists, 1969-1973, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 52-53)
    - Photographs of De Witt and Groups of Colleagues and Artists including Richard Diebenkorn, Lamar Dodd, Michael Frary, Carl Morris, William Palmer, and Fritz Scholder, 1970, undated, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 54-58)
    - Photographs of Artwork by Oliver Chafee, Michael Frary, Edward Laning, and Fletcher Martin, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Slides of Artwork by Richard Diebenkorn, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Photographs of Artwork by Ethel Magafan, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Photographs of Artwork by Norman Rockwell, undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Photographs of Artwork by William Palmer, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Slides of Miscellaneous Artwork, 1973, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 64-65)
    - Slides of Artwork not Included in the Exhibition, 1971-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Album of Photographs of the Exhibition Opening, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Audio Recording on reel-to-reel tape of Interview with DeWitt, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Audio Recording on Cassette of Interview with De Witt, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - America 1976, 1974-1978, undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Correspondence, 1977, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 71-72)
    - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Financial Material, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Exhibition Guestbook, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, 1975-1976, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Clippings, 1976-1978, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Exhibition Catalog, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Photograph of Artwork by Vija Celmins, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Slides of Miscellaneous Artwork, 1975, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Photographs of the Exhibition Opening, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Audiocassette of Interview with DeWitt, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Audio recordings on Reel-to-Reel Tapes of a Symposium on the Exhibition including panelists Michael Mazur, Susan Shatter, and Alex Katz, 1975-1976, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
- Photographs, 1970-1974, Series 3:; (Box 2; 1 folder)
  Photographs are of John DeWitt at unidentified locations, and of artists Joseph Raffael and Ann Wyeth McCoy in Hawaii.
  - Photographs of DeWitt and of artists Joseph Raffael and Ann Wyeth McCoy, 1970-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)